ok so this is probably one of the most important
slides of this lecture, for sure, but also
of the course so let us spend some time on
it and before we actually start looking at
this slide let us first reason a bit together.
So I just said that you have one CPU core
and that it is all the time changing the program
it runs. Now the way it does this is not really
that different from the way we do things in
our lives so if I am preparing dinner let us
say I want to cook some pasta so I have a
set of instructions that I need to follow
and I am going to run one instruction after
the other so first you put the water then
you warm the water until it boils then you
put the salt then you put the pasta and blah
blah blah I am going to do one thing at the
time and let us assume this is what I am doing
and I might get interrupted let us say my daughter
she needs something so she calls for me and
I stop paying attention to what I am doing
and I start paying attention to her before
I do that I will store somehow information about
what is the last thing or the last instruction
I executed about preparing dinner so I will
memorize for example that the water is warming
up but I have not yet put the salt in it before
also talking with my daughter I will also
switch to the relevant context for my daughter
I will probably check what she has in her
hands or something like this so I will stop
preparing dinner and start taking care of
my daughter I will do whatever I need to do
with her at a certain point I will be done
I might need to maintain some information
about what I just said to my daughter because
maybe I said her to go pick up something and
I need to remember what that something is
and then I will load back information about
where I was with the pasta the next thing
to do was to put the salt what I described
it is called in operating systems a context
switch and this is what is happening all the
time in each CPU core so now let us look at
the slide there are lots of terms here and
they will be introduced in the next video
but it is simple at the end of the day here
we have two processes and they are called
processes not programs because these are running
and you can run the same program multiple
times and each one is a different process
you see that interrupts and system calls appear
here too and you see that there is this PCB
which stands for process control block and
each process has its own process control block
we have process 0 and we have process control
block 0 we have process 1 and there is process
control block 1 what is happening here is
that you are executing or the CPU cores are
executing process P0 at a certain point something
happens can be a system call or an interrupt
this is my daughter that calls for me and
what the operating system does is that it
saves the context the state of process P0
and loads the one of process P1 it does a
switch in the context to move from process
P0 to process P1 then it starts executing
process P1 and when it is done it stores the
information about process P1 loads the information
about P0 and then starts executing process
P0 again there are important things here you
can already see each process can be in a different
state sometimes the process is executing sometimes
the process is not so it could be in a idle
state also you see that there are periods
of time during which no process is running
this is the time it takes to store the process
control block and to reload the process control
block of another process as you can imagine
here these times need to be minimized if you
spend most of the time doing this load/unload
of PCBs then most of your CPU time is just
wasted doing context switches as we will discuss
during the course there is a very tight connection
and cooperation between the operating system
and the hardware and that is why they (context
switches) can happen extremely fast so fast
that you do not actually perceive them and
you have this feeling of several processes
running at the same time when they are not
really running at the same time there is one
more important thing here that might sound
strange now but it is important I am talking
about the operating system as the one that
decides that it is time to stop running process
P0 and start running process P1 and do this
king of things the problem here is that I
am simplifying a bit stuff because the operating
system is not an oracle or an entity that
lives outside your computer at the end of
the day it is a bunch of instructions that
you execute as you execute any other process
so if you look at this image here where do
you see the operating system? what does it
mean the operating system decides that it
is time to stop running process P0 and run
process P1 if process P0 is being run it means
that the CPU core is running process P0 if
you assume that you have only one CPU core
(because you had operating systems even when
you had computers with a single CPU core)
how does the operating system take a decision
about switching a process? well as I will
explain one of these two processes or even
both processes might actually belong to the
operating system so you might be running process
P0 and you want to read something from the
disk then you do a system call the hardware
puts your process to sleep and wakes up the
process that belongs to the operating system
and is the process that it is about reading
something from the hard disk